<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assises holden at Winchester the 24. day of Februarie last, before Sir Laurence Tanfeild knight, Lord Chiefe Barron of the Exchequer, and Sir Richard Hutton knight, one of the iustices of the Court of Common-pleas. By Abraham Browne prebend: of the Cathedrall Church of Winton.</title>
            <author>Browne, Abraham, d. ca. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119312</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854519</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assises holden at Winchester the 24. day of Februarie last, before Sir Laurence Tanfeild knight, Lord Chiefe Barron of the Exchequer, and Sir Richard Hutton knight, one of the iustices of the Court of Common-pleas. By Abraham Browne prebend: of the Cathedrall Church of Winton.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Abraham, d. ca. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. All-de,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19945:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19945:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE ASSISES, HOLDEN AT WINCHESTER the 24. day of Februarie laſt, before Sir LAVRENCE TANFEILD Knight, Lord Chiefe Barron of the Exchequer, and Sir RICHARD HVTTON Knight, one of the Iuſtices of the Court of Common-Pleas.</p>
            <p>By ABRAHAM BROWNE Prebend: of the Cathedrall Church of WINTON.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>NOLI ALTVM SAPERE</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Edward Allde</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw. All-de.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19945:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19945:2"/>
            <head>TO SIR LAVRENCE TAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FEILD KNIGHT, LORD Chiefe Barron of the Exchequer; and Sir RICHARD HVTTON Knight, one of the Iuſtices of the Court of Common-Pleas.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloued in the Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Was requeſted very earneſtly by a right Worſhipfull perſon, that hee might haue a <hi>Copie</hi> of my Sermon, Preached at the Aſſiſes at <hi>Wincheſter:</hi> another put mee in minde of publiſhing it, and a Dedicatorie Epiſtle required. To anſwere all theſe; if I publiſh it, I ſhall ſatisfie in exhibiting the Copie requeſted: And albeit I am not ouer earneſt to haue it publiſhed, yet I may ſuppoſe, that that part of the Sermon which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Maſſe (the thing moſt of all reſpected in the ſpeech) may ſerue among other Writings for the confutation of that pretended ſacrifice. But for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory Epiſtle, to whom more properly &amp; of right doth it appertaine then to your Honours? (if it may pleaſe you to accept of it) your ſelues being the moſt principall perſons in the Auditorie, moſt iudicious to diſcerne all things then ſpoken: and being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with pleadings in Law, may iudge what validity our reaſonings haue in matters of Religion.
<pb facs="tcp:19945:3"/> The pleadings in Law are ingenious, and ought to be very demonſtratiue, ſtrong in proofe, that things may be euidently cleared before they come to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: yet this difference, that in Law-pleadings one pleadeth againſt another; In our matters one ſpeaketh, and no man in the place muſt contradict: yet we muſt not be in that reſpect more bolde, but more circumſpect; for God heareth, and many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. What I haue ſaid againſt the Maſſe, I haue read, and reſolutely approue to be the truth: and if ſhortneſſe haue made obſcurity or weakeneſſe of proofe, or inſufficiencie in a matter of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance; when it ſhall be replied, by Gods grace I will ſtrengthen the Arguments, and giue more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of teſtimony accordingly, as things are by me alledged. In pleading againſt the Maſſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other controuerſies in Religion, your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours are very competent and conuenient Iudges. For with you are handled caſes of reſtitution, if any thing be taken away: matters of truſt to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: alienations of things in that reſpect, and alterations not to be admitted, <hi>voluntas teſtatoris,</hi> the teſtators <hi>will</hi> eſpecially to be regarded, the ends propoſed in grants to be obſerued: that if the Maſſe Prieſt, were put to his triall at your iudgement ſeat, he ſhould receiue the very ſame iudgement I haue
<pb facs="tcp:19945:3"/> ſet vpon him. He muſt reſtore the Table he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, place it againe in the middeſt of the Church as our common Prayer booke alloweth, that it may be farther from an Altar, or (if not) to haue ſuch a iudgement as to be a Table &amp; not an Altar; he muſt reſtore the great Loafe he hath taken away, hauing put in ſteed of it a thin Wafer Cake, the knife muſt be brought again, alienation muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called: that the Prieſts onely muſt not participate, alteration forbidden, and to miniſter vnder both kindes, the end preſcribed by our teſtator to be kept, euen by eating the Bread, and drinking the Cup, to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2.</note> ſhew forth the Lords death vntill he come. For the Maſſe is a new inuented Religion, and as it is ſaid in Scholes, <hi>Vno abſurdo dato mille ſequuntur,</hi> Grant one abſurdity and a thouſand will follow: ſo is it with the Maſſe Prieſt, one abſurdity hath bred many abſurdities; he hath inuented a myſterie, and yet his myſterie keepeth not the rule of ſuch myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as are in the olde Teſtament, which ſhould be the patterne for all myſteries. And againe, as his myſterie agreeth not with the Scriptures, ſo the Maſſe Prieſts intention agreeth not with his Maſſe booke: that as it is ſaid, he that is out of the way the faſter he runneth the farther he is out; ſo is it with the Maſſe Prieſt, once out, neuer in. The Maſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19945:4"/> Prieſts dealing (in reſpect of God and in reſpect of the people) is like a tenure in <hi>England</hi> which I haue heard of, where the Tenant maketh proffer of a Preſent to his Landlord, but deliuereth it not, that the chiefe Lord may ſay vnto him, I thanke you for nothing. For concerning God, the fooliſh Maſſe-Prieſt vnderſtandeth not, that that which is the Prieſts portion, and that which the Prieſt eateth, (as it is in the Leuiticall Offerings) is not the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but that which is burnt is Gods offering, and the bloud ſprinkled at the mercy ſeat, is the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but he eateth all his offerings, drinketh vp all in his Chalice, and rinceth his Chalice, that he may be knowne to drink all, that God may ſay to him I thanke you for nothing: But as for the people, they may all the yeare long (excepting once a yeare when he receiueth but halfe) ſay to him we thank you for nothing. And for the Maſſe Prieſts intention not to agree with his Maſſe booke it is as euident. For his prayers are in the plurall number: and he intendeth himſelfe only. Againe, he prayeth to God, only that the oblation which the whole family had offered (meaning the Bread and Wine which the brethren had offered, part whereof was to ſerue for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion) might be made the Body and Bloud of his moſt beloued Son Ieſus Chriſt. And vpon it bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:19945:4"/> in the Inſtitution, which is for taking &amp; eating: but he intendeth not, but offering of Chriſt himſelfe for a propitiatory ſacrifice; not marking that a body broken &amp; bloodſhed is already ſacrificed; and what is once ſacrificed cannot be ſacrificed again. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour ſitting in perſon at the ſupper, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his Body broken as already ſacrificed, and his Blood ſhed, to preuent a Maſſe Prieſt for to offer him: For his ſacrifice as a Doctor of the Church <note place="margin">Gregorius Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzenus.</note> ſaith, is, <hi>inſacrificabile ſacrificium,</hi> a ſacrifice that cannot be ſacrificed againe. Beſides theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities, this is alſo not to be ouer-skipped, that when he ſaith <hi>Ite miſſa eſt,</hi> Goe your wayes, it is diſmiſſing time; the ſpeaker meaneth that ſome ſhould depart, and thoſe that remained ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate: for all might haue adored, if that only were intended, but all could not communicate: but he intendeth no ſuch thing as a Communion, that they that remaine muſt adore only, and receiue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that ſtil the people may ſay, We thank you for nothing: The truth is, the old prayers which are in the Maſs book are miſtaken: for in the prayers, what is for offering, is to be referred to thoſe offerings which the diſciples had offered for the maintenance of the Church, but the myſteries of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, were to be receiued according to
<pb facs="tcp:19945:5"/> our Sauiours Inſtitution: in ſo much that we liuing now by Tythes, thoſe prayers are out of vſe. More might be ſaid, but a Dedicatorie Epiſtle muſt not be ouerlong. The Text of my Sermon is a mattor of great obſeruation; ſhort in words, but large in meditation. Let vs looke to the ordering of our wayes, and not ſo much with them to attend an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary adorning of Temples made with ſtone, and a falſe aduancing of Sacraments: ſo ſhall wee haue better ſhewed vs the ſaluation of God; and we true worſhippers in ſpirit and truth. The people of the land haue accepted this Religion, as to pray in their mother tongue, to offer praiſes in ſinging of Pſalmes, with the Preaching of the Word if they may haue it. Lamenting much when their lot is to dwell there where they may not haue it: I write what I know. The ſumme is, if we offer praiſe, and order our wayes, we ſhall in greater confidence looke for the comming of him which is to come, euen our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, iudge to be of the quick and the dead, vnto whoſe grace I commend your Honours in all your iudgements.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in the Lord, ABRAHAM BROWNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19945:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED at the Aſsiſes holden at <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 50. v. 23.</bibl>
               <q>He that offereth praiſe, glorifieth me, And to him that diſpoſeth his waies aright, Will I ſhew the ſaluation of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue choſen this Text in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; Firſt in reſpect of my ſelfe being aged, and about finiſhing my courſe, after a long ſeruice in the miniſterie of the Word, that I might haue ſuch a Text, as would ſumme vp, if not all, yet moſt of my Sermons. Secondly, this being the time of the Aſſiſes, it would be very fitting to ſpeake of that which will be handled at the generall Aſſiſe, which is the day of Iudgement. Laſtly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to exhibit vnto you the Religion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, compleat, euen perfectly ſet out; for as much as without which we cannot be ſaued.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19945:6"/>
            <p> To performe theſe things, I haue deuided my Text into three parts. The firſt will concerne praiſing of God; The ſecond to be the ordering of waies; The third, a ſhewing of the ſaluation of God. The firſt of praiſing God, I will make inſtance thereof in the Church ſeruice, that the religion of Chriſt in the new Teſtament, may be fully diſcerned: And where it is ſaid, he that offereth praiſe (without any excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perſon) albeit the word (offereth) be the act of a Prieſt, yet I had rather ſay, that all are Prieſts, then to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt any from offering of praiſes, euen in the Church. It is ſaid in the <hi>Reuelations</hi> of Chriſt, that he hath made vs <note place="margin">Chap. 1. 6.</note> Kings, and Prieſts, vnto God, and his Father. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Yee as liuely ſtones, are built vp a ſpirituall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>houſe vnto God, to offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifices vnto God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable thorough Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> for albeit the burnt offerings of the old Teſtament are ceaſed, yet we cannot be a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar people vnto God without ſacrifices: It is a thing duly to be marked, that that part of the Temple which was called but the Porch thereof, was twice ſeuerely reformed by our Sauiour, and titled by the name of the houſe of God: our Sauiour applying that vnto it, in the Prophet <hi>Eſay, Mine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 21. 12. Iohn 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>houſe is the houſe of Prayer, and you haue made it a den of theeues.</hi> And ſo it followeth in the myſterie of the Temple, that the vpper part thereof being fulfilled by Chriſt, and in him perſonally finiſhed in the heauens, where he is now, and appeareth in the ſight of God for vs: Now nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for vs, but only that part wherein was Prayer, and Preaching: And ſo that place honoured with the title of the houſe of God. To this, that anſwereth that our Sauiour after he was aſcended, gaue gifts vnto men, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming by them, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors, Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 9.</note> no Prieſts; and I will ſay no Prieſts ſacrificing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Prieſts. Againe, the Apoſtles deſigning out their office, goe no farther then to giue themſelues continually to <note place="margin">Act. 6. 4.</note> prayer, and the miniſtery of the Word. And if their prayer be the prayer of the Church, the vnlearned muſt confirme
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19945:6"/> it by ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> vnto it. And they ſhall be but preſident Prieſts among the Prieſts, offering alike praiſes vnto God. All the congregation offereth, and they no Prieſts, nor good Diſciples that offer not. All our Church Seruice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably for offering is, Prayers, Confeſſions, &amp; prayſes: for Prayer the houſe is named by it, &amp; for confeſsions &amp; prayſes the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word in my Text is indifferent to them both: If any man obiect and ſay, that there are more things in the Church ſeruice then prayers, confeſſions, and praiſes, as reading of Scripture, the Pulpit Sermons, the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per alſo, and Baptiſme: To this I anſwer, that in all theſe, God offereth ſomewhat vnto vs, and not we to him: in the reading Statutes and ordinances, with admonitious, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and threatnings, the Pulpit ſecondeth theſe things; at the Lords Supper Chriſt giueth and we receiue: Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme offereth the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes: ſo nothing will be ours but offering of Praiſes in the houſe of Prayer: vnto which, God addeth this approbation, <hi>Hee that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Praiſes glorifieth me.</hi> This aſſertion, howſoeuer it miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trent Can.</hi> 3. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6.</note> others, it hath one moſt vehement aduerſary, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing in a Counſell: that whoſoeuer ſhall ſay that the Lords Supper is a Sacrifice of praiſe and thankſ-giuing, a bare remembrance of the Sacrifice done vpon the Croſſe, and not propitiatorie, or only to profit the receauer, neither ought to bee offered for the liuing, and for the dead for ſinnes, puniſhments, ſatisfactions, and other neceſſities, let <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhemes</hi> vpon Heb. 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> him bee Anathama. Others ſay, that there is no lawfull Common-wealth in the world, that is not made a peculiar people vnto God by a Prieſthood, diſtinguiſhed from them that worſhip falſe Gods, or no Gods at all. This muſt be anſwered, or wee haue a great defect in our Church, and my ſelfe reproued, that take hold of theſe words, as if God were now content, only with a ſpirituall ſacrifice, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Hee that offereth praiſes glorifieth mee.</hi> And to make anſwer; this Pſalme containing ſuch matter as ſhall bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable at that day, when God will call all the world
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19945:7"/> from the riſing of the Sunne, to the going downe of the ſame, vnto iudgement. Firſt of all it is ſaid, <hi>I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>thee for burnt offerings,</hi> So that wee are diſcharged from the Leueticall ſacrifice: And then commeth in theſe words, <hi>Offer vnto God Praiſe, and pay thy vowes to the moſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>high.</hi> And both theſe things are contained in my Text, and no more Sacrifices then theſe contained in the Pſalme. That which the Papiſts ſtriue for, is called by the name of the Maſſe: which thing beareth the burthen of the Church ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice with them. The thing therefore offring oppoſition to mine aſſertion, I could not but looke more narrowly into the matter, and I finde that this Reall ſacrifice of the Maſſe, is not only of thoſe things which are not named in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of which it is alſo ſaid, <hi>Negat Scriptura quod tacet:</hi> The Scripture denieth that it ſpeaketh not of: but it is in the Scripture by ſtrong reaſons, &amp; arguments contradicted. And as for the Doctors of the Church, there are the names of Prieſt, Sacrifice, Altar; but the thing not ſo: Thirdly, the practice of the Apoſtolike, and Catholike Church will not beare ſuch a thing as the Maſſe is: that is by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is contradicted; in the Doctors a verball matter, a thing of words; in the practice of the Church, a nullitie, a thing of nothing.</p>
            <p>To make theſe things appeare, I muſt firſt ſet out the Scriptures contradicting it, euen in his Maſſe prieſt, and in his ſacrifice. In this reſpect I will ſet out ſeuen faults in the Maſſe, two againſt Chriſt his Prieſthood according to the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> and fiue againſt his Sacrifice on the Croſſe; The two faults againſt the Prieſthood are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Maſſe-Prieſt will preſumptuouſly thruſt himſelfe into ſuch a prieſthood, as is proper to an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Perſon: and the Prieſthood therefore continued in him, not paſſing it ouer to any other, for ſo is the Propheſie; <hi>Thou art a Prieſt for euer, according to the order of Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech.</hi> And accordingly the Propheſie is ſo applyed, as this man becauſe he endureth for euer, hath an vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19945:7"/> Prieſthood. This word vnchangable, is otherwiſe tranſlated; a continuall Prieſthood, or a Prieſthood that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not from one to another; but <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> a Doctor <note place="margin">Serm. cont. Arianos.</note> of the Church ſaith: it is <hi>Sine tranſitione, ſine ſucceſſore:</hi> without paſſing it ouer to any other, without a ſucceſſor.</p>
            <p>The ſecond fault is, that the Maſſe-Prieſt will be ſo bold as to be of that order, that was made with an oath after this manner: <hi>(I haue ſworne and will not repent:)</hi> for this (will not repent) will not agree with a ſinner that needeth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, therefore ſaid; <hi>That the Law maketh Prieſts that haue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 28.</note> 
               <hi>infirmities, but the word of the Oath which is ſince the Law, maketh the Sonne who was perfected for euermore:</hi> ſuch a ſonne, as of whom the Father will ſay, <hi>this is my welbeloued</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> To diſcourſe of theſe two points, would require longer time then is allotted. I will paſſe therefore to the ſecond kinde of faults againſt his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, in number fiue: The firſt thing is, that in ſacrificing he will imitate Chriſt ſacrificing himſelfe vpon the Croſſe, which thing muſt not be imitated in any wiſe. This thing may be obſerued that our Sauiour Inſtituting his Supper as a remembrance of him vntill he come againe, gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as already ſacrificed: that is, his body broken and his blood ſhed; for the Sonne of God, may doe as God his Father doth, which <hi>calleth things that are not, as if they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 17. Heb. 10. 14.</note> 
               <hi>were:</hi> for concerning ſacrificing, it is as it is ſaid, <hi>with one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, he hath for euer perfected thoſe, that are to bee ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> As <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a Doctor of the Church ſaith vpon that place, <hi>Si. Medicamentum forte, &amp;c.</hi> if the Medicine bee ſtrong once applied, it will cure all together: if with one oblation he hath perfected thoſe that are to be ſanctified, he that will bee ſanctified by the repetition of the Sacrifice, ſaith the medicine is not ſtrong. The ſecond fault is, that the Maſſe-Prieſt not marking the order of the attonement in the old Teſtament, taketh in hand a worke which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly finiſh: for the attonement was not finiſhed when the Prieſt in the lower part of the Temple had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19945:8"/> offered his Sacrifice: but for to make vp the attonement, <hi>Hee muſt goe vp into the holy place, and ſprinckle the blood</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 16. 14.</note> 
               <hi>vpon the mercie ſeat:</hi> So did our Sauiour the Prieſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> when hee had offered himſelfe vpon the Croſſe, <hi>he entred into heauen</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>now to appeare before the preſence of God for vs: and ſtandeth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 24. Reuel. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>in the middeſt of the throne, as a Lambe ſtaine:</hi> This ſecond point of entring into the Holy place, is farre from a Maſſe-prieſt, that if hee ſhould boaſt that he beganne, ſay hee cannot, that according to the Leuiticalls, hee hath finiſhed an attonement. The third fault is, that to make Chriſt a Sacrifice, he conſecrateth an Altar, by which meanes he will make the better the worſe, and the greater the leſſer. For in the myſterie of Sacrificing, the Altar is greater then the Sacrifice, as our Sauiour calleth the Scribes and Phariſes <hi>fooles, and blinde,</hi> ſaying <hi>whether is greater the gift, or the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 23. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Altar that ſanctifieth the gift?</hi> True it is, the Doctors of the Church haue vſed this word Altar, without weighing of it; it was not ſeauen times purified in the fire: it may be found in them that Chriſt offered himſelfe vpon the altar of the Croſſe: but if things muſt be tryed by the touchſtone of the Scripture, the Croſſe brought nothing but curſe and ſhame to Chriſt crucified. But for ſanctifying, our Sauiour <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 13. Heb. 12. 2. Iohn 17. 9. Heb 9. 14.</note> faith plainely, <hi>I ſanctifie my ſelfe,</hi> and offered himſelfe through an eternall, or ſome reade it, holy Spirit, without ſpot, and purgeth our conſcience from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God. The fourth fault, is againſt the laytie only; vnto whom he deliuereth Chriſt ſacrificed when hee hath not ſacrificed him at all: for without blood-ſhedding no ſacrifice, and which is more, no forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. It is but a mockerie to ſay a body cannot be without blood: for a ſacrifice cannot be without blood-ſhedding where death enſueth, Chriſt ſhed his blood when he was circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and ſome otherwiſe, but the Sacrifice was not fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed before death was teſtified, euen when <hi>out of his bleſſed ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de iſſued water and blood,</hi> the vitalls of rhe heart: In the <note place="margin">Iohn 19. 34.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19945:8"/> primitiue Church therefore, the knife that cut the bread was called <hi>Sacra Lancea,</hi> the holy ſpeare, as making a ſuppoſed iſſue of blood for the Chalice. If God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould deale with the popiſh Laytie according to the myſterie of Sacrificing, none of them haue forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſinnes: And by this meanes all Pardons from the Pope are fruſtrated, becauſe they neuer are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the remitting blood of Chriſt: for out of the ſacrifice (Blood) not any capableneſſe of pardon. The fift fault is, that when he hath made an end of his owne ſacrificing, and eating of the Body and drinking of the Blood of Chriſt: he putteth a conſecrated Cake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Pixe at the vppermoſt end of the Church cloſe to the wall, which is not agreeable to the myſtery of the old Temple: for our Sauiour in the myſtery of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bearing the perſon of the Mediator, repreſented in the incence Altar, for interceſsions and prayers: that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar ſtood belowe and right before the Mercie ſeate, ſo <note place="margin">1 Kings 6. 22.</note> that by this meanes in their Church God is excluded, and if that they will ſay that he is in heauen, why then is not the Mediator in Heauen, that their Church order may be according to the truth of things? For Chriſt is in heauen, to make Interceſsion for vs. But this conſecrated Cake is affirmatiuely made, the god of the Chriſtians, who in the myſterie of our Chriſtian religion is the Mediator as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, one God and one Mediator: in ſo much that a Counſell decreed, that the Church prayers ſhould <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Con. Carthag.</hi> 3. <hi>Can.</hi> 13.</note> be made vnto God in the name of the Mediator Ieſus Chriſt: for albeit any perſon of the Trinitie, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon, yet ordinarily God is to be prayed vnto, and Chriſt the Mediator, which in our Church booke, is moſt commonly obſerued.</p>
            <p>But here is the ſcandall to Infidels of all ſorts, that this is the God we make ſhew of, carrying him by proceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the ſtreets, and euery where worſhipped: yet the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19945:9"/> Cake hath no prerogatiue as other things haue had; as <hi>Manna</hi> appointed by Gods ordinance to bee reſerued, <note place="margin">Exod. 16. 24.</note> was free from corruption; that it may ſeeme to be a ſtrong argument that this Cake made God, is not his ordinance being ſubiect to mouldineſſe, and the eating of Myce: and I haue read that being carryed in the winde, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten blowne out of the Pixe, was clipped and made leſſe: O indignitie! that I will ſay of this laſt point according to a phraſe in the Prouerbs: Sixe things I hate, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth (in thus abuſing of our Sauiour) I deteſt and abhor, and ſo end Scripture reaſon, and paſſe to the teſtimony of the Doctors of the Church.</p>
            <p>To repeate the Doctors of the Church in the multitude of their teſtimonies, would be too much for a whole Sermon, much more for a piece of a Sermon: But to proue that which I haue affirmed, that the Maſſe is but a verball thing in the Doctors; and as they ſport in Schooles, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erum est in vocibus non in rebus,</hi> true in words but not ſo in deeds: I will ſet out vnto the Doctors an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to anſwer, and a place of Scripture to expound. The obiection made againſt the Chriſtian religion was, that they had neither Temples, nor Altars, nor Images. This obiection hath anſwer from the Doctors: the firſt that anſwereth ſhall be <hi>Origen,</hi> who liued 200. yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Tract. in Leuit.</note> Chriſt: and he for Altars nameth the heart, and our <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 9.</note> prayers for the ſacrifice: <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 7.</note> Doctor of the Church, being about <hi>Origen</hi> his time, ſaith <hi>non ſacrificamus ſed glorificamus:</hi> wee ſacrifice not but glorifie. In ſaying we ſacrifice not, hee cannot forget ſpirituall ſacrifices: therefore meaneth ſuch a reall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as the Maſſe is; and the Doctor forgetteth not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſacrifices, when he ſaith we glorifie, for that anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to my Text. An other Doctor of the Church <hi>Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 2.</note> liuing 300. yeares after Chriſt, ſaith to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; <hi>Putatis nos occultare quod colimus, ſi delubra &amp;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19945:9"/> 
               <hi>aras non habemus.</hi> You thinke that we hide that wee worſhip, becauſe we haue neither Temples, nor Altars. If the Chriſtians God was hidden, it was no where to be ſeene, neither in the Church, nor out of the Church; If no Altars, no Sacrifice reall, no Maſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cirillus</hi> an Archbiſhop much to bee regarded in this matter, he liued about 400. yeeres after Chriſt; the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection he receaueth from <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata: who if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reall ſacrifice as the Maſſe had beene but intimated in the Church, he would haue diſcerned it, being once a Reader by Office in the Chriſtian Church: but the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is <hi>Lata via euntes, mentalem cultum perficientes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>con: Julianus.</hi>
               </note> Going the broad way, wee make a mentall or minde-worſhip.</p>
            <p>And now if you expect more teſtimonies: mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is the obiection ceaſed not long after him, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion was better vnderſtood with the reaſons thereof, that <hi>Chriſoſtome, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Hierome</hi> for ought I haue read, make not the like mention thereof: And as for <hi>Iuſtin</hi> the Martyr an inhabitant of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a Doctor of the Church moſt ancient, about 160. yeeres after Chriſt, his Church-ſeruice is ſo like ours, that from him we haue teſtimony for ours.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Dioniſius</hi> that auncient Doctor, as is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he maketh a great ſhew at the firſt of ceremoniall matter, but it endeth with this, the Biſhop communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the reſt he exhorteth to communicate, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with thankſ-giuing, and thus much for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</p>
            <p>The place of Scripture which is to bee expounded by the Doctors is that in the Prophet <hi>Malachie,</hi> where it is thus written: <hi>From the riſing of the Sunne, to the going</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ch. 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>downe of the ſame, my name is great among the Gentiles, and in euery place, Incence ſhall be offered vnto my name, and a pure offering; for my name is great among the Heathen</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19945:10"/> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> This place ſaith the Papiſt, ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidenly proueth the Maſſe, that it cannot be denied: but then I muſt make the Doctors of the Church, if they ſo expound it not, vnskilfull in the interpretation of the Scripture, preferring moderne and new Writers before them. The force of their aſſertion ſtandeth vpon theſe words (pure offering) which can agree to none but vnto Chriſt offering: which I eaſily agree vnto, for our offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings if they be pure, they are but pure by a fauourable grace, being as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith <hi>acceptable through Ieſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But to come to the Doctors, the firſt that I will bring in is <hi>Irinaeus,</hi> of whoſe writing they preſume moſt: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4, <hi>cap.</hi> 32.</note> his words are, that our Sauiour gaue counſell to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to offer vnto God out of his creatures, firſt fruites (not as if he needed them,) but that they ſhould not bee vnfruitfull, or vnthankfull. That which is bred of his creatures, he tooke it, and gaue thankes ſaying, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and the Cup likewiſe, that which is of that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and is with vs confeſſed to be his Blood, and taught the new oblation of the new Teſtament, which the Church taking from the Apoſtles in the whole world, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto God.</p>
            <p>Theſe words to him that is affected to the Maſſe, may ſeeme to ſound ſome ſuch thing, but he is deceaued: for albeit the words of the Lords Supper be brought in, as that he ſaid of the <hi>Bread<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that it was <hi>his Body,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the <hi>Wine,</hi> to be <hi>his Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od,</hi> yet the body of Chriſt, and his Blood, are not the offerings; which a Prieſt muſt only offer; but the Bread only and the Wine are the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, which not Prieſt but Diſciples offer.</p>
            <p>In the primitiue Church therefore the Diſciples offered at the Table, new Corne, Grapes, Oyle, and Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and theſe decreed by a Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to haue the <note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>us.</note> name of oblations: that now I will conclude againſt the Maſſe, that ſo learned a Doctor comming ſo neere the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19945:10"/> Lords Supper, as bringing out the words of the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and handling ſo curiouſly withall, the place of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachy,</hi> yet not hit vpon the Maſſe ſacrifice: ſurely it may bee well ſuppoſed the Maſſe was not in his dayes. To proceede to the reſt, for of theſe Offerings the Bread and Wine are not the Body, and Blood of Chriſt, but the materialls of the things, as the Doctor ſaith, which God hath no neede of, we haue, I meane Chriſt himſelfe: So the oyle was for Lamps, may be as the Frankenſence for odours; That at the firſt had ſo the name of Offerings, that the Maſſe Prieſt may miſtake them in the Canon of his Maſſe, to be the things hee ſtriueth for. <hi>Tertullian</hi> is <note place="margin">Aduerſus Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> the next Doctor, he ſaith, that the pure ſacrifice is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſacrifice, and a pure conſcience: <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, it is the myſticall Table, and the reuerent ſacrifice vpon it. <note place="margin">In Pſalm. 95.</note> This is it you will ſay, but the Doctor ſaith, it is done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Altar, then not ſacrificed by vs, but offered as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſacrificed by Chriſt: for if no Altar then no Maſſe. <hi>Hierome</hi> that Doctor ſaith, it is the prayers of the Saints. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, it is religious Hymnes, and holy Prayers: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>menſtr. L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Contra Iuli. l.</hi> 9. <hi>De ciuit. l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 25. In Heb. ch. 8. In Malac.</note> 
               <hi>Cyrillus</hi> ſaith, it is meant of Chriſtians worſhipping God euery where. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> that Doctor interpreteth it of Saints offering themſelues: <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, our heauenly Altar is our faith, in which wee offer our daily Prayers: <hi>Theodoret</hi> doth expound the place of ſpirituall ſacrifices: Theſe Doctors being the moſt famous Doctors of the Church, and all in their Expoſitions, not hitting vpon the Maſſe, how can it then be true, that this place cannot be otherwiſe expounded, then of the Maſſe? But I ſuppoſe S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the Doctor of vs Gentiles, doth expound the place, where he ſaith, <hi>I will therefore that men pray exery</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>where, lifting vp holy hands,</hi> and as it is tranſlated) <hi>pure hands without wrath, or doubting.</hi> And thus for the Doctors of the Church, and to the Papiſts, I ſay, they are rather in this matter, <hi>Sophiſticae verborum quam Diſcipuli veritatis:</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19945:11"/> Sophiſters of words, not Diſciples of the truth: As one ſaid to a Ieſuite in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> that hee had taught them to vſe Sophiſtrie in the ſimplicity of Chriſts Religion.</p>
            <p>But to auoide all Sophiſtry, I make a third triall, which is the practiſe of the Church: where I ſay the Maſſe is a nullity, euen a nothing; and here I make vſe of the Plea at Common Law: where when an auncient Graunt is in queſtion, they enquire after the Vſier of it, as they terme it: how that was continued from the firſt time of the Graunt: The like will I doe in my Plea againſt the Maſſe: And I will aske the Maſſe-Prieſt, where his Altar ſtoode in olde times? and I will anſwer him my ſelfe, for it ſtood in the middle of the Church: What elſe? it had railes about it, and thoſe called the Chauncell. What was vpon it? I anſwere a great Cake, or Loafe. What beſides? a knife, called <hi>ſacra lancea,</hi> the holy Speare, beſides alſo other <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie.</note> diſhes. What was done there? I anſwere the Bread and Wine was deliuered to them that reached out their hands to receiue it. In what garments did he ſtand? I anſwere, the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours (as it is confeſſed by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. lib.</hi> 7. 18. <hi>Roſar. B. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae.</hi>
               </note> themſelues, celebrated <hi>in quotidianis veſtibus,</hi> in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they ware euery day. This being the Vſier in aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times: Now I will aske a Maſſe Prieſt whether this be his Maſſe or not? and withall, I will bid him come downe from his Altar, and ſtand at a Table, in the middeſt of the Church, with a great Cake, or Loafe vpon it, his knife by it, and then ſay (if he can ſay ſo) we are of a new Religion. And now I will anſwer when the olde Religion went out, euen when the Table that ſtoode in the middle of the Church, euen a boord Table, was turned into a ſtone Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, placed at the vpper end of the Church, the loafe of Bread turned into a little round thinne Wafer-Cake, and the knife out of vſe: and holy veſtments deuiſed for the Prieſt; confeſſed therefore it muſt be, that the Maſſe is a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19945:11"/> latter, and a new inuention, not the Inſtitution of Chriſt: And if you aske when this was done? let the Maſſe Prieſt tell it: for a man will come by his goods, though he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell when, and at what time the Thiefe ſtole it. But he may anſwer, it is the Church that hath done it: that is, I ſay men deuiſed it, for in Scripture ſpeech, when God hath ſet downe what he will haue done, the after doings, are called the inuentions of men, as when our Sauiour alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth out of the Prophet, <hi>That the feare of God was taught</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 15. 9.</note> 
               <hi>by the precepts of men;</hi> thoſe men were the Elders of the Church, the Gouernours of the Church, that is, the Church: But as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>I hate inuentions, but thy law</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 113,</note> 
               <hi>doe I loue:</hi> And now I will apply thoſe words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> as <hi>ſtand in the wayes, and looke, and aske after</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 6. 16.</note> 
               <hi>the olde way, and walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therein, and you ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules.</hi> And if you will haue proofe of theſe things: firſt for the boord Table. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> telleth of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, <note place="margin">Ep. ad Bonifa, Durandus,</note> that in their anger brake the boords of the Altar. And let not the word Altar trouble you, for it is but a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed word from the olde Teſtament; for it was a boord Table: and as for the Loafe, a Writer of theirs ſaith, that in olde time, it was a great Loafe, ſufficient for all the Communicants: and why is it not, that which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, as that <hi>we are all partakers of one Bread?</hi> which thing is ſo <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 17.</note> obſerued, that <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> that Doctor of the Church ſaith vpon that place in this manner; <hi>Not of another body this man, of another body that man, but all of one body are fed and nouriſhed.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>Knoweth he not that euen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 86.</note> 
               <hi>now he is to eate part of the body of that immaculate Lambe?</hi> Strange kindes of ſpeaches of two ſuch famous Doctors, and contrary to the Councell of <hi>Trent;</hi> That decreeth that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Sacri. Euch. can.</hi> 3.</note> Chriſt muſt be taken to be whole, in Diuinitie ſoule and body, and in euery parcell of the bread, for euery man by himſelfe to participate: But theſe Doctors, bewray ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter, as that the Lords Supper is to be eaten in an
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19945:12"/> vnderſtanding ſo: not ſo indeede. In an vnderſtanding, all the houſhold of Gods Elect haue eaten, doe, and ſhall eate, of that onely Body, which was broken at the Croſſe. And eating it in ſuch an vnderſtanding, we ſhall then eate it ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, in the deede it ſelfe. No feeding to the ſpirituall feeding: ſo true a feeding, and ſo ſubſtantiall, that to it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreeth all that our Sauiour ſpeaketh, in the ſixt of <hi>Iohn,</hi> of eating of his Fleſh, and drinking of his Blood: As to this thing alſo we are directed by our Sauiour his own ſpeech, ſaying: <hi>It is the ſpirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the words that I ſpeake, are ſpirit, and life.</hi> And the concluſion of this note is, that theſe two famous Doctors by their ſpeeches, haue ouerthrowne both tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Maſſe.</p>
            <p>But to proceede in the matter in hand: that the place for the Table, was the middle of the Church, one onely proofe will ſerue, which is <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius li.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Gerſon.</hi>
               </note> Church, made for Chriſtian Religion, ſo placed it. And it is reported by a Writer of theirs, that when the Pope commaunded that the Tables ſhould bee made of ſtone, (may be for the iogling of it) hee would haue for himſelfe, a Table of boords. And now I haue ended my ſpeech concerning Scripture, Doctors, and the Vſier of the Church; none of them teſtifying the Maſſe: It may be it will be ſaid, if the Maſſe be taken out of the Church, a thing ſo comely, and glorious in his ceremonies, the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt will be but a bare Religion. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that if it be bare, it will fit well enough to that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which muſt be, in <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>in truth,</hi> according to our <note place="margin">Ioh. 4. 23.</note> Sauiour his owne ſaying, onely decencie and order muſt not be neglected. And when the Religion of Chriſt ſhall be thus ſtripped of this outwardly glorious Prieſt, it will receiue the better iudgement from the wiſe. A graue Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, or a ſeuere cenſuring Poet, will giue a truer iudgement then thoſe Gouernours of the people, that to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19945:12"/> pleaſe the vulgar ſort of men, holding them to ſome Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; deuiſe for them ſuch glorious ſhewes, not caring whether the thing be true, or falſe, or agreeable to Gods word, or not agreeable. A wiſe Philoſopher will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt inhabitation of vertue in a threed bare cloake. They were wiſe men, which adored Chriſt lying in a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: But ſuch baſeneſſe needeth not, as pompe alſo nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not, <hi>in medio virtus,</hi> vertue may be neither. A Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher reading of the Goſpels, and marking our Sauiour his ſpeaches ſaid, he was the wiſeſt man that euer ſpake: He looked not for any authority of the world in our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but conſidered his ſpeeches: And concerning glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Churches, a Poet will ſay, <hi>In templis quid fuit aurum:</hi> What doth gold in the Temples, if it be (ſaith hee) the Gods will not thanke you; if not, they will not blame you. What ſaith <hi>Cato? Si Deus eſt animus, &amp;c.</hi> If God be a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he is to be worſhipped with a pure minde. <hi>Numa</hi> had three ſayings, as that the Gods cared not for bloody Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: Againe, better things were not to be preſented by worſe things: ſuch as the Images be made of (no not of gold, for it is but thick clay.)</p>
            <p>The third thing was, that the whole life of man, was to be ſpent in Religion. If a Papiſt ſhould bring an Heathen Philoſopher into his Church, and ſhew the goodly Imagerie, and painting therein, he would aske him what elſe? for theſe Images haue mouthes, and cannot ſpeake, as when they brought him a childe, to behold the beauty of him, he ſaid to the childe: <hi>Loquere my pner vt te vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am:</hi> Speake childe that I may ſee thee: hee reſpected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vertue, not outward ſhewes. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>In humilitate hnius ſacrificij, non eſt tiphus, nec cothurnus,</hi> In the humility of this Sacrifice, there is neither pride, nor masking, like Players. The ſum is the Religion, is not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by gewe-gawe fooliſh men, but by them that are graue and ſober.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19945:13"/>
            <p> The Papiſt when he would gaine a Diſciple, he obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth againſt vs, that our Religion is to eaſie; no auſterity of life, for want of faſting: againe, bare of all comely ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies: Both theſe obiections are not otherwayes to be anſwered then by the wiſedome that is in Chriſts Religion, As for faſting, to anſwer in wiſedome two wayes, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wee eate not fleſh to pamper our fleſh: but as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Timothy, Drinke a little wine for thy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 23.</note> 
               <hi>ſake, and for thy often diſeaſes:</hi> The like to be in eating of fleſh, and this being true without diſſimulation, then it will be ſeconded; that ſuch liberty is in Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that nothing is to be excepted againſt, which is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>with thankes-giuing</hi> vnto God: A good Diſciple that beleeueth it; A faithfull deuider of the Word that preacheth it. But for comely ceremonies, as farre as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie goeth, wee muſt goe along with them: a fault to haue our houſes ſwept, and foule Churches; faire ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at home, and ragged Pewes. Our Sauiour being to anſwere the obiection of faſting, made his anſwere three wayes; firſt, that <hi>new wine was not to be put in olde bottels:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 9. 14.</note> Secondly, that nothing would gaine them to the truth; for <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> came faſting, and they ſaid he had a diuell: he came eating, and they ſaid hee was a glutton: The third anſwer, which muſt ſtand for all, is, that wiſedome is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified of her owne children: Theſe rules obſerued, they muſt haue an anſwer picked out of them: But if we faſted with them, their faſting a matter of no ſuch hardneſſe; ſhould wee gaine them? that the anſwere will be the laſt (which is) that wiſedome is iuſtified of her children. And our Sauiour will ſay for all iudgements, <hi>If I ſay the truth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 46. 47</note> 
               <hi>why doe yee not beleeue me? hee that is of God heareth Gods word.</hi> As the wiſdome of Chriſt in his Religion, framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſpirit and truth, ſeemeth fooliſhneſſe to the wiſe men of this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld: ſo let the wiſedome of the wiſe men of this world, be fooliſhnes to vs, that are Chriſts Diſciples.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19945:13"/>
            <p> I will deuide our Church actions into three ſorts. The firſt is our Confeſſions and Praiſes, in the houſe of Prayer: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The houſe of Prayer is Gods houſe: and for theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and Praiſes, they haue their approbation out of the Text: As God himſelfe ſaying in his owne perſon, <hi>He that offereth praiſes glorifieth me,</hi> where the word Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth will anſwere to the obiection of wanting glorious ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of Church ſeruice, euen that hee that offereth praiſes, glorifieth him. The ſecond ſort of things are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and the Lords Supper; of theſe no queſtion, onely the Lords Supper for his name, by the Maſſe Prieſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what excepted againſt; as bearing the name of Supper, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> then their deuiſed ſacrifice of the Maſſe; yet for this alſo I anſwer with that Propheſie: <hi>Thou doeſt prepare a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before me in the ſight of mine aduerſaries.</hi> I am the bolder <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> ſo to ſay, becauſe two Doctors of the Church <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> make vſe thereof: as ſeeking proofe for a Table: whereby they ſhew, that albeit the name of Altar be vſed, yet a Table muſt be proued; for that the Churches act was at a Table, not at an Altar: And ſo it ſerueth for an Argument againſt the Maſſe. The Act of the Pulpit is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the third: which muſt be alowed, for albeit the houſe which is the houſe of God, be named by prayer, as the principall act therein (our Sauiour ſo ſaying) yet the Euangeliſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addeth, that <hi>he taught daily in the Temple,</hi> and then <note place="margin">Luke 19. 46.</note> this Act may not want his Propheſie. I will allude at the leaſt to that place of a Pſalme, where it is ſaid: <hi>An hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 72. 16.</note> 
               <hi>of Corne ſhall be in the earth, euen in the top <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and the fruit thereof ſhall ſhake like the trees of Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, and the children ſhall flouriſh out of the Citie like graſſe.</hi> What is this handfull of Come, which ſhall be in the dayes of Chriſt? for the words of that Pſalme concerne him, and his dayes, and ſaid to be in the top of the mountaine: let that Sermon in the mountaine be it; yet what is the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Church, if not the Pulpit, the higheſt place of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19945:14"/> the Church? and what more anſwereth to an handfull of Corne, then the Preachers Text: for the <hi>ſeede</hi> the Sower ſowed, <hi>was the word of God.</hi> And when this handfull which <note place="margin">Luke 8. 11.</note> is the Text, is enlarged by Expoſitions, and Applications, how well may be ſaid, that the fruit thereof ſhaketh, like the trees of <hi>Libanus.</hi> And how fitly ſhall the Auditorie be thoſe children, that flouriſh out of the Citie, and ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Preacher as thicke as graſſe? And I will ſay, that I may better take vp this Propheſie; for the Seede of the word ſowed in the Pulpit, then the Maſſe Prieſt can take it vp: for his baked Cake, vpon the top of his ſhauen crowne. For he is bold, ſo to apply it: though hee ſhake no fruit, except he ſhake his lockes in that his dumme ſhew when he acteth his Maſſe.</p>
            <p>The Kingdome of Chriſt is knowledge and aboundance of knowledge, as it is ſaid by the Prophet, that <hi>in the dayes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſay.</note> 
               <hi>of Chriſt, knowledge ſhall abound, euen as waters vpon the ſea:</hi> And who is he that is a man of grauity, and wiſedom, but that he will ſay it is a glorious ſight, and a glorious Church built of liuely ſtones, to ſee men and women of all degrees; and youthes of all ages, come into the Church with their Bibles, and Pſalme-bookes, to heare the Word, and to ſing Pſalmes, and praiſes to the glory of our God? Theſe acts would become the greateſt Emperour in the world.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, that he ſung in the Church: But what neede I ſpeake of an Emperour? Chriſt our <note place="margin">Math. 26. 30.</note> Sauiour the patterne of Maieſtie and grauity did ſing. The Prophet <hi>Hoſee</hi> willeth the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to <hi>offer the Calues</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſe. 14. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of their lips:</hi> but to offer prayers by telling of prayers which they vnderſtand not, be they not lips of Calues and not of men? It is ſaid of a Philoſopher, that hee neuer laughed but once, and that was when hee ſaw an Aſſe ſo gingerly to eate a thiſtle: I ſuppoſe he would haue laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed once more to ſee a man like a great boy, to ſtand with a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19945:14"/> payre of Beads at his girdle, and to take them with great deuotion to tell prayers in a tongue he vnderſtandeth not.</p>
            <p>But I will follow theſe matters of the Church no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but will come to the ſecond part of my Text, which is in theſe words, <hi>And to him that ordereth his waies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> But to bring in this ſecond part, I muſt ſet downe a common Church for vs Chriſtians like the Temple of the <hi>Iewes</hi> whereunto all reſorted, of all Sects and of all manners; <hi>Phariſes,</hi> with their Leuen, <hi>Saduces</hi> denying the Reſurrection: with ſinners of all ſorts, none accepted but the vncircumciſed: vpon this confuſe mixture in the worſhippers in one houſe commeth in that queſtion. <hi>Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle? who ſhall reſt in thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 15. 1.</note> 
               <hi>holy hill?</hi> The like is here, though not propoſed in a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but affirmatiuely ſet downe, as <hi>to him that ordereth his waies aright, I will ſhew the ſaluation of God.</hi> God is glorified in his houſe, when in it common praiſes be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him, but the ſaluation of God ſhall not bee ſhewed but vnto <hi>him that ordereth his waies aright.</hi> I muſt deuiſe ſuch a Church that all muſt come into, And what need I ſay deuiſe a Church, I know where I ſtand, and before whom I ſpeake at the Aſſifes: But my deuiſed Church is none other then the Church of <hi>England</hi> as now it is, which hath in it foure principall notes, Authenticall and Catholike to the deſigning of ſuch a Church, And they vnreſiſtable truths, as theſe.</p>
            <p>There ſhall be no Images in the Church to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; This is agreeable to the ſecond Commandement, ſo euidently practiſed by the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that you need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether they worſhipped any: for in their Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, as in their Temple they had no Images to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: that their Prophets may freely ſpeake againſt Images as it appeareth in the Propheſies committed vnto them by a certaine relation from the holy Ghoſt. This continued to this day: They cannot without great offence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19945:15"/> giuen of Chriſtians, to ſee that ſecond Commandement put out of their Catechiſme, and the worſhip of Images groſſely practiſed euery where.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is, that the whole Church-Seruice ſhall be in their mother Tongue as we ſay, that is knowne vnto them: For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as in a matter of great abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, asketh the queſtion when on bleſſeth in the Spirit, how ſhall he that occupieth the roome of the vnlearned, ſay, Amen. at the giuing of thankes? ſeeing he knoweth <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 28.</note> not what thou ſayeſt.</p>
            <p>The third is concerning the Lords ſupper: that it bee giuen and receaued vnder both the kindes: euen of Bread and alſo of Wine alike conſecrated: For who can deny that our Sauiour did not ſo inſtitute it, and ſaid, <hi>Doe this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>as oft as you doe it in remembrance of me:</hi> and ſo deliuered it vnto Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that it might in that manner be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in the Church. This to be obſerued is neceſſary to be required, that in a matter of ſo great importance there may be no defect in the Church.</p>
            <p>The fourth is, that there be propoſed but one true and liuing God to receaue the prayer, and for Mediator none but our Sauiour the Sonne of God; as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> euen in that place where he appointeth for the Church ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and prayers to be made in it, and ſaith, <hi>There is but one God and one Mediator betweene God and man, the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>man Chriſt Ieſus who gaue himſelfe a ranſome for vs.</hi> No perſon of the bleſſed Trinity, but may haue inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euen in the Church: but Saints (whoſoeuer) are no mediators for that place: For I will ſay as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in a ſmaller matter, <hi>They were neither crucified for vs, nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>wee baptized in their name.</hi> This is the Church, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, that to contradict this Church, if Gouernours of people ſhall perſecute their Subiects, if they will not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Imager, nor haue their Church Seruice in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue, not receaue in one kinde, nor admit more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19945:15"/> Mediators then Chriſt, they are execated and indurated, blinded in their vnderſtanding, and hardned in their hearts: On the contrary ſide, if Gouernours ſhall not tollerate any to ſay, we will worſhip Images, haue our Seruice in the Latine tongue, though not vnderſtood of vs, and will but vnder one kinde receaue at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and will haue more Mediators then one: If by the ſeuerity of their powers they compell them to come into this vndoubted Catholike Church, they ſhall doe it cleerely with a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>There was one named <hi>Apelles</hi> as it appeareth in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtories, who was of this opinion, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Doctrines were not to be inquired after, but euery one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide as he hath beleeued, and euery man to be ſaued that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in Chriſt Crucified, ſo that hee be found in good Workes.</hi> This opinion was holden for erronious, and ſo it is. For albeit <hi>Phariſes</hi> and <hi>Saduces</hi> came into the Church or Temple altogether, yet our Sauiour ſpake vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the Phareſie, denouncing a <hi>Woe vnto them:</hi> and <note place="margin">Math. 23. Math. 22. 29.</note> alſo confuted the Saducie: And excommunications euer haue beene executed, though making differences in the executions.</p>
            <p>There are two ſorts of men, which profeſſe Recuſancie againſt this Church, which in reſpect of theſe foure points, I dare affirme to be Apoſtolike, and a true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church: the one beareth the name of a <hi>Recuſant:</hi> the other is called a <hi>Separatiſt.</hi> I make to my ſelfe ſome difference betweene them, as the other an Aduerſary in doctrines of Faith; this agreeing in doctrine, but diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the Ceremonies of our Church. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the other diſlike of doctrines, and this man diſtaſte our Ceremonies: why ſhall not both of them, come to a common Church where there will bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers, Supplications, Thankeſ-giuing for the King and for the Kingdome, with other neceſſities, for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19945:16"/> of men, in occupying on the Seas and on the Eearth? The God is common to both, the Mediator common to both, yea the Lords Supper as common to both, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is common: The Recuſant Papiſt being with vs a profeſſed Chriſtian, differeth not from vs in ciuility of life, vertues and good workes: The maine point of theſe ſeparations is only Scriptures, and only Chriſt, two mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great importance: let them grant that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are only the tryall for matter of Saluation tending to eternall life, which thing the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſought in them as our Sauiour affirmeth, and withall make Chriſt the only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator; <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 39.</note> the reconciliation will be at hand. As for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiſt wee agreeing in doctrines, our Ceremonies of greateſt note in offending being but three in number, as the Surplis, kneeling at the receauing of thoſe bleſſed Signes giuen by Chriſt, as children kneele when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue their fathers bleſſing: the third croſſing in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: For the fewneſſe of them like a thinne cloude, which will nothing hinder the glorious ſhining of the Goſpell through them; nothing burdenous, and which will much cleere the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church from any great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: he that is in the Pulpit with his handfull of Corne ſowing the word of God, his iudgement by them is not any whit Captiuated, and brought into ſubiection, but may freely ſay when he hath croſſed a childe in Baptiſme, that the Baptiſme was perfected before the Croſſe came. O what golden dayes haue beene loſt by this ſeparation? And now I haue made this Preface to my ſecond part: I will frame a queſtion like that, as <hi>Who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle, and who ſhall reſt in thy holy hill?</hi> Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to anſwer is made, <hi>He that walketh vprightly and worketh righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſo I will make the like queſtion: to whom will he <hi>ſhew the ſaluation of God?</hi> And anſwer ſhall bee <hi>to him that ordereth his wayes aright.</hi> In the Hebrew it is, <hi>to him that ſhall put his wayes.</hi> And I will make to bee,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19945:16"/> 
               <hi>putting his way into a vow;</hi> And ſo it ſhall anſwer to that which ſucceedeth the burnt offerings, and ſaid, <hi>Offer vnto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 14.</note> 
               <hi>God praiſe and pay thy vowes vnto the moſt High.</hi> For there is no way better then to put our wayes into a vow: into which order of proceeding, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth aright: For the childe at the baptiſme putteth his waies into a vow: and when he commath to bee Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed he is asked of it, and he anſwereth, that they did promiſe and vow three things in my name, meaning Godfathers and Godmothers, whom otherwiſe wee call Witneſſes. And now our waies are put into vowes, they are debts, and anſwer to that in the Lords prayer, where we are willed to craue that our heauenly Father would <hi>forgiue vs our debts,</hi> for what fooliſhneſſe were it to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our vowes to be other, then thoſe that are ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in our baptiſme, which are diligently to be marked, as to <hi>forſake the Diuell and all his workes, the pompes alſo and vanities of this wicked world, and the ſinfull luſts of the fleſh, to beleeue the articles of the faith, and generally to keepe Gods commandements.</hi> Who but a Papiſt would expound in triuiall matters? And to draw to the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the matter, <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt was the firſt that began the Miniſterie of our new Teſtament, and applyed vnto himſelfe, out of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> his office to be a Crier in the Wilderneſſe; ſaying, <hi>Prepare yee the wayes of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 3. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, make his pathes ſtraight, euery valley ſhall be filled, and euery mountaine ſhall be brought lowe, and the crooked ſhall be made ſtraight, and the rough waies ſhall bee made ſmoothe.</hi> How manifeſtly doth this of the Pſalme of <hi>orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of wayes</hi> proceed, ſo confirmed by a Prophet, and executed by <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt more then a Prophet. And that we may thinke that theſe, were not words without deeds &amp; a practiſe accordingly, it may well appeare by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe that <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt his preaching had: for it fell right into the <hi>ordering of waies</hi> in ſuch ſort, that particular
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19945:17"/> perſons one by one enquired of him how <hi>to order their wayes? The people</hi> (and they no doubt the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) <hi>came vnto him, and asked of him what ſhall wee doe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>then? and he anſwereth vnto them and ſaith, hee that hath two coats let him impart to him that hath none, and hee that hath meat let him doe likewiſe. Then came alſo the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans to be Baptized and ſaid vnto him, Maſter what ſhall we doe? And he ſaid vnto them, aske no more then that which is appointed you. And the ſoldiours likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him ſaying, and what ſhall wee doe? and hee ſaid vnto them doe violence to no man, neither accuſe any man falſely, and be content with your wages.</hi> And by theſe we may make a rule for others, as no doubt he did: Who did the like to <hi>Herod, rebuking him for keeping his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>wife.</hi> And at one word, this is the truth of which our Sauiour ſpake of to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>the true worſhippers muſt worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 4. 23. Rom. 12. 1.</note> 
               <hi>truth, in offring vp our bodies in a true rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntance, and holy ſacrifice vnto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Apoſtles had medled with lawes of carnall commandements, they had tranſgreſſed the rule: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they meddle not with any thing, but with matters of truth, in ſquaring out duties for ſubiects to their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and high powers with reciprocall duties betweene husband and wife, father, childe, Maſter, ſeruant: And generally this to be Gods Commandement, <hi>to beleeue in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>the name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, and to loue one another as he hath commanded.</hi> If this method had heene conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued betweene Paſtor and Flocke: the new Teſtament had beene alwaies ſeene in his true colours: which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was bedawbed with gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, but vnkinde and vnnaturall ceremonies. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Primitiue Church kept his matter of <hi>ordering of waies</hi> a long time: And to giue you a view thereof I will bee ſo bold, as to deuide this Auditorie into theſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19945:17"/> particular eſtates; As here are honourable Iudges, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of peace, Counſellors at law, Gentlemen, Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, Merchants, Handycraftſ-men, and Husbandmen: For the Iudges (ſuch honourable and wiſe perſons) I will ſay no more then God bleſſe them, and of the reſt I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in ſo ſhort a time ſpeake particularly; But that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſomewhat may be ſaid of <hi>Waies,</hi> I will take out two, which in the primitiue Church were in ſome queſtion concerning their waies: thoſe are the <hi>Merchant,</hi> and the <hi>Soldiour.</hi> The Merchant was called into queſtion as not hauing the right courſe of a trade, becauſe hee is nothing laborious as others are, but eaſie, ſelling whole ſale, of no action, neither in hand or in ſpeech: for properly that is a trade, which getteth gaine by his labour, and after gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, returneth ſtill to his labour: as the Handycraftſman maketh his worke, gayneth, and returneth to his worke againe; ſo the Plowman ſoweth and reapeth and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the Plow againe: ſo vocations of words; haue their gaines, and their returnes to labour againe. For it was ſaid to <hi>Adam, in the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eate bread, till thou returne to the earth, for out of it waſt thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>taken, becauſe thou art duſt, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne.</hi> Notwithſtanding this queſtion of the Merchant was not alike defined, but men of good iudgement diſſented: and I ſuppoſe that <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> would not haue made any exception againſt him who excluded not the <hi>Publican,</hi> neither is the Merchant an idle man, but much occupied, and looketh vp vnto the heauens to haue ſucceſſe and bleſſing from God. You may ſay that rather they might haue made exception againſt him whom I named a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman: vnto that I anſwer, that our kinde of Gentlemen, were not extant in their dayes: But I will helpe to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them to take heed, that that which is in the booke of <hi>Wiſdome</hi> be farre from them, as to ſay <hi>of the pleaſures and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Wiſdome.</note> 
               <hi>paſtimes of this life, this is our portion, this is our lott:</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19945:18"/> Remember what <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to his ſonne being in hell torments, <hi>Thou in thy life time receiuedſt thy good things.</hi> As for the <hi>Soldiour,</hi> the exception againſt him was, not to be receaued into the miniſterie of the Word.</p>
            <p>But there are more kindes of trades, and one there is not ſo eaſie to be condemned: becauſe the Law is to be the ground of his action; but he is ſo often in law, that he is leſſe in charitie, and filleth whole pariſhes with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe. To diſcribe him, I muſt borrow a tearme from the common Law, which may bee, comprehendeth not ſo generally theſe kinde of trades: But the tearme is a Common Barretor: With theſe kinde of men no treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes muſt be taken vp by neighbours and bretheren, in one faith and one Church: but all muſt be tryed by law: that the offender if he refuſe that tryall, muſt redeeme his peace with a great price. This trade is ſo violent, ſo hurtfull, and ſuch a cunning extortion, that our Sauiour both remembreth it, and giueth counſell to his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>If any man will ſue thee at the law, and take away</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 5. 40.</note> 
               <hi>thy coat, let him haue thy cloake alſo.</hi> If therefore Chriſts Diſciple muſt deliuer coate and cloake, whoſe Diſciple is he that taketh them?</p>
            <p>There is an other Tradeſman, if wee may call him a tradeſman; I meane the Vſurer, tollerated in Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, <note place="margin">Pſal. 15. 5.</note> &amp; condemned in the word of God: None of the Diſciples of Chriſt, in whom there muſt be nothing but that which is perfect, that we may be like to our Maſter, who was perfect. His Diſciples therefore muſt not lend, looking for ſomething againe; but lend, looking for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againe. And in the new Teſtament, how can it be, that to him ſhall be ſhewed <hi>the ſaluation of God,</hi> when in the old Teſtament <hi>He ſhall not dwell in the holy hill.</hi> In this thing they are both a cenſured euill, by the word of God, and an euill end will be the encreaſe of riches in their great abundance to them that vſe it. The abundance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19945:18"/> of riches ſo blindeth his iudgement, that he ſeeth no euill, but thinkes that he hath God by the finger, when he hath the diuell by the fiſt. In the olde Law one might not lend in Vſurie to his brother according to the fleſh, and may he now lend to his brother according to the ſpirit? Let the Preachers of the Word, and deuiders of the Word take heede leaſt while they teach ſome vſuries ſmall, that they may be done: they by ſo teaching and ſo doing, become leaſt in the Kingdome of heauen: Let the Diſciple hearken vnto his Maſter, and heare Chriſt ſaying; <hi>If ye loue me keepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements.</hi> A Lawyer being asked concerning Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 15.</note> vpon the Sabaoth day, anſwered, that the Arreſts were good in Law: but the parties that executed the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts puniſhable; ſhall we ſo anſwer for the Vſurer, that his vſurie is good in law, but the Vſurer culpable? ſo that <hi>he ſhall not dwell in the holy hill.</hi> And to ſpeake ſomewhat of Arreſting on the Sabaoth day: whereby I ſay, <hi>our wayes are not ordered aright:</hi> how can that be good in the law of any Common-weale, that breaketh any one of the ten Commandements? the ten Commandements, are not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubtill, hard to be diſcerned, but groſſe, euen the law of nature. Let vs put a God, (and what Nation doth not put it) no leſſe can be then to haue one ſet day to worſhip in. Breake that day ſo commanded, and where then is our Religion? To put out his day, and to ſet out another, would require good warrant: Put, breake this, and to put in no other will be irreligion. The Sabaoth day to be kept ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhould be accounted, though not ſo expreſſed in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, yet neceſſary in his vnderſtanding; but he vſurpeth another Phraſe as Arreſts to be good, any commandement from God notwithſtanding: and ſo a priuate man will make iudgement, for the whole Kingdome. Is it not brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an holy Sabaoth day, to doe occupations of the world on the Sabaoth day, as to Cart and Plow? and is it nothing to vſe violence, and to draw to priſon, the Iaylor
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19945:19"/> to attend, Scriuener to be called for, Obligations to be made, money to be payed? Iudge righteous iudgement, ſhew not Art of Law in the lawes of men againſt the law of God.</p>
            <p>There is a Propheſie in the Scripture concerning the Church of Chriſt, as that <hi>the Wolfe ſhall dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall be with the Kid, and the Calfe, and the Lyon, and the fat beaſts together, and a little Childe ſhall leade them:</hi> What are theſe beaſts, but men of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers natures which haue ſubſcribed to the faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt? ſome proud and haughty in minde, ſtrong, and by nature rauenous, fat ſome in the pleaſures of this life, and in the abundance of wealth; others meeke, gentle, poore and miſerable: and who is this Childe that doth leade them vp and downe to their paſtures and feeding in the word, but that Miniſter and Preacher of the Word? in reſpect of ſuch a great worke, as a Childe weake and ſimple, yet ordereth their wayes: And when the common Barretor and his neighbour, the Vſurer and his Captiue ſhall ſit before the Childe, in one Church, if not in one Pew, the common Barretor ſhall learne a leſſon of peace, charity, and the Vſurer taught mercie: and his Debtor learne to borrow and pay againe. Shall the borrower be as an excommunicate perſon, for a miſerie that may be could not be auoided? and ſhall God leeſe his right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe man will haue his? deſtruction and ruine is prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, to that place where man is preferred before God. If it be ſaid that <hi>if we loue not our brother whom wee ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how will we loue God whom we ſee not?</hi> Let theſe cruell men haue their brethren brought into a place, that they may ſee them to make experience if loue of brother be in them, if not, how then the loue of God? The concluſion of theſe ſhall be, take heede of this generall Aſſiſe Pſalme; ſaying, <hi>What haſt thou to doe to declare mine ordinances, that thou ſhouldeſt take my couenant in thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19945:19"/> 
               <hi>to be reformed, and haſt caſt my words behinde thee?</hi> Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Light is come into the world: but men loue darkneſſe more then light. For euery one that doth euill ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the light, neither commeth to the light, leaſt his deedes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 19,</note> 
               <hi>ſhould be reproued.</hi> But he that doth the truth, commeth, to the light, that his deedes may be manifeſt, that they are wrought in God.</p>
            <p>It is no ſmall inducement for men, to runne to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Religion, becauſe there is to be had, this ordering of wayes very particularly, like as it was done by <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> when they came to be baptized of him, confeſſing their ſinnes: euen at an auricular confeſſion to doe it, a grace if it be a grace, not to be had with vs will be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: I cannot denie, but that it is an <hi>ordering,</hi> but not an <hi>ordering aright</hi> of the wayes of Chriſtians. For that <hi>orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> is curſorie after this manner; A deputed Prieſt for that purpoſe, a moſt particular enumeration and telling of ſinnes, pennance proportionably enioyned, and abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>To examine theſe in order as they are ſet downe, The firſt a Prieſt Deputed for Confeſſions: And where in the new Teſtament is this Deputed Prieſt? Is it euery Prieſt? S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> albeit he had ſaid, <hi>If any man be ſicke, let him call the Presbiters, Elders or Prieſts,</hi> as they will haue it: <hi>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chap. 5. 14.</note> 
               <hi>pray ouer the ſicke perſon, and to annoint him:</hi> yet in the very next verſe, ſpeaking of Confeſſions of ſinnes or faults, ſaith: <hi>Confeſſe one to another ſinnes or faults,</hi> neither doth he will the Prieſt to enioyne it, but biddeth the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans one to another to confeſſe ſinnes: And if it be but to pray one for another, that Act is not onely for Prieſts, but common with euery Chriſtian: and it is not <hi>abſolue one another,</hi> but <hi>pray one for another, that they may be healed:</hi> And the prayer is of a iuſt man, but onely Prieſts are not iuſt.</p>
            <p>And for the ſecond point, which is ſo particular an
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19945:20"/> enumeration and telling of ſinnes, this I will ſay, that the deuiſing of queſtions about the breaking of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, by the Confeſſor, is worthy the reading, that we may ſee the multitudes of treſpaſſes and offences for our inſtruction: And farther, to helpe euen for the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things in our ſoule much amiſſe: but the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a crime and haynous fault, how can it be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? I haue read it in a printed confeſſion booke after this manner. That ſince I was at Confeſsion, or as the words are, firſt I acknowledge my ſelfe guilty vnto <hi>Almighty God, vnto our Lady St. Marie, and to all the Company of heauen, and to you my ghoſtly father, that ſith the time of my laſt Confeſſion I haue offended my Lord God greeuouſly, and ſpecially in the ſeauen deadly ſinnes:</hi> and comming to the ten Commaundements, he ſaith: <hi>I haue ſinned fleſhly with perſon that beene wedded, and other moe, and more would, if I might haue had time and place.</hi> Such a Confeſsion had neede to be auricular, tolde in the Prieſts eares, and kept cloſe. But what pennance ſhall be ſet out for ſuch a man? The ſaying is, Hee that will not pay it in his body, muſt pay it in his purſe. And will that be an <hi>ordering of wayes?</hi> And ſhall hee be thus abſolued from time to time? then will it not be waſhing a Sow that walloweth in the mire. You Papiſts ſay, that our Religion is an eaſie Religion, you meane becauſe you faſt often in abſtaining from eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of fleſh (for that is all) you taske your ſelues with Prayers, and vndergoe penancies: but if this <hi>ordering of wayes</hi> bee your Religion, your Religion will bee the eaſier Religion; for it is eaſier to mortifie the fleſh, then to mortifie the deedes of the fleſh: you call it the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of penance; if penance be the Sacrament, you will deceiue the more perſons laden with ſinne: and to thinke themſelues lighted of the burthen of ſinne, when ſinne ſtill from time to time ladeth them. Speake plainly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſay it is repentance, and forgiueneſſe is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19945:20"/> as our Sauiour ſaith to vs Preachers, ſetting downe our Commiſsion. <hi>Thus it is written, and thus it behooued</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 24. 46.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe againe the third day, and that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes ſhould be preached in his name among all Nations, beginning at Hieruſalem.</hi> But you tranſlate the word <hi>repentance</hi> by the word <hi>penance:</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chriſt ſaid, that <hi>penance ſhould be preached.</hi> And from whence haue you this word <hi>penance?</hi> is it from thence that your Latine Tranſlation ſaith, <hi>Agite paenitentiam?</hi> but how diſſolutely do you abuſe the grauity of the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator? For when he meant to ſpeake home, as wee ſay, and to the purpoſe, tranſlateth <hi>doe repentance,</hi> anſwerable to our conuertion, and <hi>ordering our wayes aright,</hi> according to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greeke:</hi> you Tranſlate him in your <hi>Engliſh</hi> by your Confeſſors tearmes as doe <hi>pennance:</hi> But to returne from ſpeaking any more to them; the truth is, the ordering of wayes muſt be done by an effectuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, euen a turning from our euill wayes, that wee may be found alwayes in ſinnes great and leſſe, well tolde euen by a Confeſſors booke, to bee vpon the mending hand. This is publiſhed in our Common prayer, where repentance and forgiueneſſe are ioyned in our abſolution: the application of which abſolution we leaue to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of all hearers as they repent: and not to be a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall donation or graunt to any that repenteth not. And this is <hi>the ordering of wayes</hi> in our Church, where truthes ſhould bee, not deceptions and falſhoods. Repentance muſt bring in the abſolution, not any Sacrament, no not thoſe two noble Sacraments of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> will with vs abſolue an vnrepentant ſinner: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you apply them to Infants, vnto whom knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of repentance is not yet come. And now we may ſee why the Church is rid from the law of carnall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which were to ſome but clokes for their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, to all, burthens hard to beare: for all commaund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19945:21"/> of God muſt be kept; albeit they be carnall rights, and therfore the not ſleeping ſinne and tranſgreſſion wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of an expiation and an attonement: and now in the new Teſtament the Church ſeruice eaſie, as he that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth prayſes glorifieth God: ſo God himſelfe ſaying. But when we come to this ſecond point, which is <hi>ordering of wayes:</hi> then wee are come to that ſtraight gate, that leadeth to eternal life: into which few enter, and thereby true <hi>that many are called but few choſen.</hi> St. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>In many things we offend all of vs.</hi> And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> will not <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 2.</note> denie but that we may ſinne, though hee ſay afterwards, he that is borne of God ſinneth not: meaning by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in any ſinne neuer ſo little. It is ſaid of the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that he is not out of worke all the yeare long, for he is changing of ground, breaking vp of grounds, fallowing, plowing, weeding, reaping: no more is the Saint of God out of worke all his life time: and repentance will finde worke, for the Paſtor and Teacher, for the Flock and the Diſciple: And when we are thus labouring in repentance, let vs hearken to him that ſaith, <hi>Come to me all yee that are we arie, and laden, and I will eaſe you, take my yoke on you,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 11. 28.</note> 
               <hi>and learne of me that I am meeke and lowly in heart, and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules, for mine yoake is eaſie, and my burthen is light.</hi> Theſe words no doubt are ſpoken vnto them that labour in conuerting and turning ſtill from this, and that euill way euen as men wearied: finding the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſtill heauie. And this my Text will haue a good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie, and will anſwere well to that our Sauiour his voyce; and that it is ſaid in my Text, that wee muſt <hi>order our wayes aright:</hi> and it commeth in after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>And vnto him that ordereth his wayes aright, I will ſhew the ſaluation of God.</hi> This <hi>ſhewing of Gods ſaluation,</hi> is the third part of my Sermon, and maketh my worke a perfect worke, that I ſhall by Gods grace fulfill my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which was to exhibit the Religion of Chriſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19945:21"/> for as much as without which we cannot be ſaued. For vnleſſe when I will ſpeake of offering praiſes, and ſo glorifying God, I bring not in euery one of thoſe three perſons of the bleſſed Trinity; God will be vnperfectly glorified. And this thing is ready to be performed in theſe words, which are, <hi>I will ſhew the ſaluation of God.</hi> I ſay, the three perſons are here ready to be ſhewed vs. For who is he that can ſhew <hi>the ſaluation of God,</hi> vnleſſe it be the <hi>holy Ghoſt?</hi> and what other ſaluation vnder heauen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Ieſus?</hi> as for God, he is named: And concerning the holy Ghoſt, that he muſt <hi>ſhew the ſaluation,</hi> it is eaſily to be proued, becauſe the <hi>ſaluation</hi> is ſuch a thing as <hi>eye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaw, eare neuer heard of, and neuer entred into the heart of man,</hi> euen <hi>Ieſus Chriſt crucified: to the Iewes a ſtumbling</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 23. 1 Cor. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſtone, to the Grecians fooliſhneſſe. Where is the wiſe? where is the Scribe? where is the Diſputer of this world?</hi> by Chriſt crucified, <hi>God hath deſtroyed the wiſedome of the wiſe, and hath brought to nothing the vnderſtanding of the prudent,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 19.</note> and the Princes of this world, <hi>if they had knowne it, would</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>they haue crucified the Lord of glory?</hi> We are ſaid to be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Spirit, but I ſuppoſe that none of vs will ſay, that wee doe miniſter the Spirit but by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>none can ſay that Ieſus is the Lord, but by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 3.</note> neither Diſciple nor yet the Teacher. If the Wiſe, the Scribe, the Diſputer could not finde it out, we are not wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of our ſelues then they: What is it to ſhew a thing to a man, ſet you it neuer ſo neere him (albeit he can ſee) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ayre be lightned, by which they may ſee? The holy Ghoſt hath lightned the vnderſtanding of man, and withall will conuince the world of ſinne, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not in Chriſt. When the day is broken and the Sun vp, he that cannot ſee then is blinde indeede: ſo now that the holy Ghoſt is come and lightneth the world (which thing how farre it reacheth who can tell) whoſoeuer ſeeth nor Chriſt crucified, to be <hi>the ſaluation of God,</hi> is blinde,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19945:22"/> and to bee holden for blinde. And as there are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in ſeeing, ſome ſeeing better, ſome worſe; ſo Chriſt crucified, to be <hi>The ſaluation of God,</hi> is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeene of ſome then of others. It is an eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for vs to ſhew to a man that Chriſt Ieſus is <hi>the ſaluation of GOD,</hi> if ſhewing bee to ſay ſo, and to preach ſo, but to bring it aright into the heart, and to beleeue with my vnderſtanding that Ieſus dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our ſinnes, will require an influence of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>There is great difference in ſhewing of a ſtarre, if it were to be ſhewed betweene an Aſtrologer, and a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triman, euen about the Creation of the world, as if the Country-man were asked whether might be better ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, his Apple-tree in his Orchard, or one of the little Starres in the Skie? It may be it would not bee rightly anſwered, we are ſo earthly; and therefore dull becauſe we are earthly: but an Aſtrologer if he wete to ſhew the Stars, he will not only ſhew it according to his ſituation, bigneſſe, motion, but according to an influence it hath to vs-ward. The holy Ghoſt if hee ſhew <hi>the ſaluation of God</hi> in Chriſt Ieſus, he will ſhew it by an influence in vs, which the Aſtrologer cannot doe, and by that influence ſhew an influence in Chriſt Ieſus to vs-ward, both for Iuſtification by faith, and Sanctification by a new birth: and then with ioy wee ſhall ſay the holy Ghoſt hath ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vs <hi>the ſaluation of God.</hi> And for <hi>the ſaluation of God</hi> to be the ſecond Perſon in the Trinitie as no Chriſtian will denie, ſo he the leſſe a Chriſtian that maketh not the ſecond Perſon in the Trinitie all <hi>the ſaluation of God.</hi> As here he is named, becauſe a time appointed would come, when we ſhould readily name him, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neither is there ſaluation in any other, for there is none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder heauen giuen among men, whereby wee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19945:22"/> 
               <hi>muſt be ſaued.</hi> In the old Teſtament it is ſaid, <hi>Hearken O</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael thy God is one God.</hi> To vs alſo in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Goe yee therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 28. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the holy Ghoſt.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>There are three that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>beare record in heauen, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one:</hi> So to conclude, I will ſay that by this bleſſed Trinitie, our Religion is not only ſtyled, but confyned: beyond theſe three Perſons we muſt not goe.</p>
            <p>Angels muſt not be worſhipped, neither yet any Saint: yet there is one Saint which approacheth neere to the bleſſed Trinitie, euen the Mother of Chriſt in a right as it were, that ſhe was his Mother, though hee neuer called her Mother, but Woman. She hath matched him if not gone beyond him in Pſalmes, Hymnes, and prayers: This iniurie hath beene too long in practiſe, but now I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is come to the higheſt: For the Ieſuits to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the iniury done vnto Chriſt, firſt nameth himſelfe by the name of Ieſus: yet as if Ieſus were but a Sonne: though I dare ſay, they thinke not that Ieſus had mo bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren: they commend their ſocietie, not to Ieſus but to the Mother, as their Patroneſſe and Protectrix. A braine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke ſocietie, who will not ſay? (As lamentable it is) that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that great Champion concludeth his worke with, praiſe be to God and to the bleſſed Virgin the Mother? leauing out the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt; and ſo the Papiſts in their ſalutations and farewells, as Midwiues in childe-birth ſay deuoutly, not knowing how blaſphemouſly, God and our Lady helpe you. For who that feareth God dare ioyne a creature with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the Sonne of the Father? But it is enough, to point at theſe things for this time. My ſpeach is to better Chriſtians; let vs offer praiſe, that God may be glorified:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19945:23"/> And notice muſt be taken of that which followeth: euen that <hi>To him that ordereth his way aright, ſhall bee ſhewed the ſaluation of God:</hi> And to that bleſſed Trinitie, the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, be all honour, praiſe and glory, now and euermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19945:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
